Kimberly A. Dill-McFarland, PhD

Postdoctoral Teaching and Learning Fellow University of British Columbia 2.504 - 2350 Health Sciences Mall, Vancouver, BC Canada V6T 1Z3 1-778-681-1828; kdillmcfarland@gmail.com; in 💟 💟 kdillmcfarland

OBJECTIVE: Industrial or academic career in the application, improvement, or expansion of bioinformatics and reproducible research.

Microbiology PhD with 7+ years experience in microbiome research and data science education. Expertise in next-generation sequencing including library generation, data processing, and statistical analysis. Effective communicator to both expert and novice audiences with experience teaching one-on-one and in large courses. Specific skills include:

General

- Amplicon sequencing and metagenomics (Illumina, 454)
- Reproducible research (Github, Rmd)
- Multi-disciplinary collaboration
- Diverse communication strategies

Computational

- Unix/Linux
- R/RStudio
- Python
- Git
- mothur
- OIIME

Statistical

- Uni- and multivariate linear models
- Dimensionality reduction (PCA, nMDS)
- Co-variance and correlation
- Cloud resources Sparse dataframes

EXPERIENCE

08/2017 - present

Post-doctoral teaching and learning fellow, Microbiology & Immunology, U. of British Columbia

- Direct Experiential Data Science for Undergraduate Cross-disciplinary Education (EDUCE) including a team of 3 teaching assistants
- Design and implement data science curriculum in R/RStudio, command line tools, and cloud resources across 7 undergraduate courses
- Promote open science and reproducible research through curriculum development and dissemination on GitHub
- Secured independent funding for EDUCE (\$160K+)

07/2018 - present

Post-doctoral research fellow, ECOSCOPE

- Coordinate data science workshops for Ecosystem Services, Commercialization Platforms, and Entrepreneurship (ECOSCOPE)
- Refine online content and act as primary webmaster

07/2016 - 06/2017 Post-doctoral research associate, Bacteriology/Sociology, U. of Wisconsin-Madison

- Investigated the relationship between the human gut microbiome and long-term behaviors using the Wisconsin Longitudinal Study (WLS)
- Applied multiple regression analyses with confounder and multiple comparison correction in R
- Navigated large, longitudinal survey databases using R and Git

08/2011 - 06/2016 Graduate research assistant, Bacteriology, U. of Wisconsin-Madison

- Thesis: Assessing the impact of diet on microbial succession, growth, and milk production in dairy cows
- Designed and implemented amplicon sequence analysis pipelines in mothur and R on both local and remote resources
- Collaborated effectively with diverse international researchers resulting in numerous publications as first, middle, or corresponding author
- Communicated research to expert and general audiences through oral. poster, and writing mediums
- Mentored high school, undergraduate, and graduate students

08/2008 - 05/2011 Undergraduate research assistant, Biology, U. of Puget Sound

- Thesis: Investigating maltose metabolism in *Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus*
- Utilized semi-quantitative RT-PCR to measure gene expression
- Acquired independent funding through the American Society for Microbiology (\$10K)

EDUCATION

2011-2016	Ph.D. Microbiology, U. of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI. GPA: 4.00
2007-2011	B.S. Molecular and cellular biology , Minor mathematics, U. of Puget Sound, Tacoma, WA. GPA: 3.84

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

*co-first authors For full publication list

Dill-McFarland KA*, Tang Z*, Kemis JH, Kerby RL, Chen G, Palloni A, Sorenson T, Rey FE†, Herd P⁺. 2019. Close social relationships correlate with human gut microbiota composition. Sci Rep 9: 703. doi: 10.1038/s41598-018-37298-9

Dill-McFarland KA, Weimer PJ, Breaker JD, Suen G. 2018. Diet influences early microbiota development in dairy calves without long-term impacts on milk production. Appl Environ Microbiol 85(2): e02141-18. doi: 10.1128/AEM.02141-18

Vogt NM, Kerby RL, Dill-McFarland KA, Harding SJ, Merluzzi AP, Johnson SC, Carlsson CM, Asthana S, Zetterberg H, Blennow K, Bendlina BB†, Rey FE†. 2017. Gut microbiome alterations in Alzheimer's disease. Sci Rep 7(1): 13537. doi: 10.1038/s41598-017-13601-y

NOTABLE ACCOMPLISHMENTS

2017, 2018, 2019	Session moderator/convener at the American Society for Microbiology (ASM) Microbe meeting
2016	Microbiome Digest's Best Microbiome Paper
2016	Sigrid Leirmo Memorial Award for peer mentorship and support
2009, 2010	American Society for Microbiology Undergraduate Fellow